Guide to the Bacon Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Bacon family papers
1641-1939
1724-1939
MS 46
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
35.25
(54 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, newspaper clippings of a historical and religious nature, journals, and other papers of the Bacon family. Included are sermons and writings of Leonard Bacon; papers and journals of Leonard Woolsey Bacon and Benjamin Wisner Bacon; correspondence and printed material pertaining to the affair of Delia Salter Bacon and Alexander MacWhorter, a licentiate; and correspondence about the scandal between Henry Ward Beecher and Theodore Tilton regarding Beecher's affair with Tilton's wife, Elizabeth Tilton. Additional papers include diaries of Leonard Bacon; notebooks, letterbooks, manuscripts, and printed matter concerning the Congregational Church in Connecticut; correspondence, manuscripts, printed matter, newspaper clippings, and photos of four generations of the Bacon Family; and correspondence of Leonard Woolsey Bacon.
Bacon family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts from various members of the Bacon family ranging from 1940-1996.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Materials in Part II, with the exception of some materials in boxes 1, 2, and 7, are available on microfilm (HM 65). Patrons must use microfilm instead of originals.
Existence and Location of Copies
Letters relating to the Amistad case are available on microfilm (275 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM2.
Sermons and theological lectures of Leonard Bacon also available on microfilm (15,775 frames on 17 reels, 35mm.) from Scholarly Resources, Wilmington, Delaware.
Biographical / Historical
Leonard Bacon (1801-1881) was a clergyman, educator, and writer. Leonard Bacon was active in many theological associations and church organizations. He was pastor of the First Church of New Haven from 1825 until his death in 1881. Reverend Bacon was an ardent abolitionist and a member of the Underground Railway prior to the Civil War. He was first married to Lucy Johnson (1800-1847) and then to Catherine Terry (1813-1882).
Benjamin Wisner Bacon (1860-1932), B.A. 1881. Born January 15, 1860, in Litchfield, Connecticut. Died February 1, 1932, in New Haven, Connecticut.
Father, Reverend Leonard Woolsey Bacon (B.A. 1850, M.D. 1856, D.D. 1879) son of Reverend Leonard Bacon (B.A. 1820; D.D. Hamilton 1843; LL.D. Harvard 1870) and Lucy (Johnson) Bacon, of New Haven and Boston. Mother, Susan (Bacon) Bacon; daughter of Nathaniel Almoran and Almira (Selden) Bacon, of Lyme, Conn. Yale relatives include: Benjamin W. Bacon, '47 (uncle), and his sons, Leonard B. Smith, '94, and Winthrop D. Smith, '96; Rev. Edward W. Bacon, '69 D., and Rev. Thomas R. Bacon, '72 (uncles); Alfred T. Bacon, '73 (uncle), his sons, Roger T. Bacon, ex-'11 S., and Alfred H.T. Bacon, '14, and his daughter Agnes W. Bacon, '24 Art; and Leonard Bacon, '09, Wallace G. Corwin, '17, Leonard W. Bacon, ex-'17, and Selden D. Bacon, '31 (nephews).
Hopkins Grammar School, Coburg Gymnasium, Germany and College de Genève, Switzerland. First Berkeley Premium in Latin composition Freshman year; first dispute appointment Junior and Senior years; second Winthrop Prize Junior year and Townsend Senior years; member Freshman Football Team; substitute on University Football Team Junior year and member Senior year; member Yale Orchestra; graduate member Elihu Club (elected 1916).
B.D. 1884 (on University Football Team while in Divinity School); ordained to Congregational ministry 1884 and pastor at Lyme, Conn., until 1889; pastor in Oswego, N.Y., 1889-1896; instructor in New Testament Greek at Yale 1896-97; Buckingham professor of New Testament criticism and interpretation 1897-1928 and professor emeritus since 1928; internationally recognized scholar of New Testament criticism; M.A. Yale 1892; D.D. Western Reserve 1893, University of Breslau 1911, Harvard 1914, and Yale 1929; Litt.D. University of Syracuse 1895 and Oxford 1920; LL.D. Illinois College 1904; delivered first Kent Shaffer Memorial Lectures at Yale 1930; also gave Earl Lectures at University of California 1911 and 1924, Hibbert Lectures at Manchester College, Oxford, 1920, and Lowell Lectures 1921; president of Society of Biblical Literature an Exegesis 1902-03 and managing editor of its journal 1907-08; resident director of American School of Oriental Study and Research at Jerusalem 1905-06; in 1928 through his negotiations, Yale received concession from the British Government to excavate a portion of ancient city of Jerash (Gerasa) in Palestine, in cooperation with British School of Archaeology; representative of the department of New Testament science at World's Congress of Arts and Sciences at St. Louis Exposition 1904; author: The Genesis of Genesis (1891), The Triple Tradition of the Exodus (1894), Introduction to the New Testament (1900), The Sermon on the Mount (1902), The Story of St. Paul (1904), Modern Religious Problems (1909), The Beginnings of Gospel Story (1909), The Bible for Home and School (1909), The Fourth Gospel in Research and Debate (1909), The Founding of the Church (1909), Commentary on Galatians (1909), Jesus, the Son of God (1911), The Making of the New Testament (1912), Theodore Thornton Munger, New England Minister (1913), Christianity Old and New (1914), Is Mark a Roman Gospel (1919), Jesus and Paul (1920), The Teaching Ministry for Tomorrow (1923), He Opened to Us the Scriptures: A Study of Christ's Better Way in the Use of Scripture (1923), The Apostolic Message (1925), The Gospel of Mark (1926), The Story of Jesus (1927), Studies in Early Christianity (1928), Studies in Matthew (1930), and Kent Shaffer Memorial Lectures (1930); his manuscript on the Gospel of John, entitled The Gospel of the Hellenists, has been prepared for publication early in 1933 by his literary executor, Professor Carl. H. Kraeling, of the Yale Faculty; author also of numerous pamphlets; had contributed to Journal of Biblical Literature, Anglican Theological Review, Biblical World, Yale Review, Harvard Theological Review, Journal of Religion, American Journal of Theology, Expositor, New World Magazine, New Republic, Yale Scientific Magazine, The Independent, and New York Sunday Times; on American editorial board of Hibbert Journal 1908-1918; managing editor of Annual of American Schools of Oriental Research 1922-23 and 1924-25; editor of Leonard Bacon, a Statesman in the Church by Rev. Theodore D. Bacon, '83 S. (1931); honorary member Oxford Society of Historical Theology; member New York Reform Club, Good Government Club, Law and Order League, Civil Service Reform Club, National Council for Social Service in Connecticut, Victoria Institute of London, League of Nations Non-Partisan Association, and the Church of Christ in Yale University (acting pastor 1908-1916); secretary and treasurer of Yale Divinity School Alumni Association 1920-29 and of Connecticut Branch, Divinity School Alumni Association, 1916-1922; secretary of Class of 1884 D. since 1923.
Married May 27, 1884, in Norwich, Conn., Eliza Buckingham, daughter of William Appleton and Eliza Coit (Buckingham) Aiken, and sister of Alfred L. Aiken, '91. Children: Dorothy Buckingham, ex-'09 Art the wife of Heathcote M. Woolsey, '07; and Benjamin Selden (B.A. 1911, LL.B. 1916).
Death due to coronary thrombosis. Buried in Grove Street Cemetery, New Haven. Survived by wife, daughter, son, four grandchildren, four sisters, Margaret W. Corwin, the wife of Professor Robert N. Corwin, '87, S. Almira Bacon (Ph.D. 1911), Mabel G. Ripley, the wife of Philip F. Ripley, and Elizabeth R. Greene, the wife of Prescott M. Greene, '03 S., two brothers, Selden Bacon, ex-'83, and Leonard W. Bacon, '88 and '92 M., and a half brother David L. Bacon, '16 S. His oldest brother, Nathaniel T. Bacon, '79 S., died in 1926, and another brother, Rev. Theodore D. Bacon, '83 S., in 1930.
The Benjamin Wisner Bacon biography is taken from Yale University Obituary Record, 1931-1934, pages 53-55.
Separated Materials
Friedrich Giesbrecht, Die Berufsbegabung der Alttestamentlichen Propheten [ The Gracious Calling of the Old Testament Prophets ?], 1897, printed, removed and sent to Divinity School.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, newspaper clippings of a historical and religious nature, journals, and other papers of the Bacon family. Included are sermons and writings of Leonard Bacon; papers and journals of Leonard Woolsey Bacon and Benjamin Wisner Bacon; correspondence and printed material pertaining to the affair of Delia Salter Bacon and Alexander MacWhorter, a licentiate; and correspondence about the scandal between Henry Ward Beecher and Theodore Tilton. Additional papers include diaries of Leonard Bacon; notebooks, letterbooks, manuscripts, and printed matter concerning the Congregational Church in Connecticut; correspondence, manuscripts, printed matter, newspaper clippings, and photos of four generations of the Bacon Family; and correspondence of Leonard Woolsey Bacon.
Custodial History
Formerly owned by Mrs. Francis Bacon, Mrs Robert Corwin, the Trowbridge Estate, and H.D. Dana.
Families; Indians of North America; Journalism; Medicine; Women; Middle West; New Haven (Conn.); United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; Clippings; Diaries; Journals (notebooks); Photoprints; Scrapbooks; Sermons; Clergy; Historians; Bacon, Benjamin Wisner, 1860-1932; Bacon, Leonard Woolsey, 1830-1907; Bacon, Leonard, 1802-1881; Bacon family; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University -- Students
- Original accession, 1729-1936; Part I
  Scope and Contents
  Part I consists of correspondence, papers, newspaper clippings and journals of four generations of Bacon family members—David Bacon (1771-1817) to Seldon Bacon (1861-1946). It thus provides a wealth of material which is especially pertinent to major social and religious issues of the latter half of the 19th century. The greater part of the correspondence and papers are those of Leonard Bacon (1802-1881), clergyman, educator and writer. The collection contains many of his articles on various religious and political topics. His sermons were printed in many publications and his funeral orations were well known and reprinted by many of his colleagues. His extensive correspondence with his family, friends, and political leaders is included in the collection.
  Arrangement
  Part I is arranged in four series: Series I, Correspondence, contains letters between the entire Bacon family as well as friends and associates, and forms the bulk of the collection. The letters are arranged chronologically, headed by a description of the correspondence from 1817-1881. Series II, the Subject file, contains various legal and business documents and papers of the Bacon family, biographical data, lists of Leonard Bacon's discourses and publications, and other miscellaneous items. Series III, Manuscripts, contains writings of the Bacon family, material pertaining to church organizations, reports and minutes of various clubs and committees, writings of others, and unidentified or anonymous writings. The final section, Series IV, contains printed matter, consisting primarily of newspaper clippings, magazine articles and pamphlets, and news clipping scrapbooks, all relating predominately to religious and social issues, such as church affairs, temperance, and slavery, but also to a wide range of other topics.
  - Correspondence, 1800-1936; Series I
    This series contains the correspondence between four generations of members of the Bacon Family as well as correspondence with friends and associates. A great part of the correspondence is that of the Reverend Leonard Bacon. The first folder in the series is a description of correspondence between the years 1817 and 1881 and the rest of the folders are arranged chronologically. The series ends with a folder for undated correspondence, arranged alphabetically, and a letterbook of L. W. Bacon, 1874-1876 (largely illegible).
    - Description of Correspondence, 1817-1881 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1800 March-1824 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 2-19)
    - [Circa 1824-undated] (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - 1825 May 20-October 12 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - [1825]-undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - 1826 January 2-1834 December 26 (Box 2, Folder 24-39)
    - 1835 January 3-1838 December 31 (Box 3, Folder 40-52)
    - 1838-undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - 1839 January 1-December 31 (Box 4, Folder 54-56)
    - 1839-undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - 1840 January 17-1845 December 29 (Box 4, Folder 58-74)
    - 1846 January 7-1847 December 15 (Box 5, Folder 75-81)
    - 1847-undated (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - 1848 January 8-December 12 (Box 5, Folder 83-86)
    - 1848-undated (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - 1849 January 1-1852 December 28 (Box 5, Folder 88-96)
    - 1853 January 3-December 26 (Box 6, Folder 97-101)
    - 1853-undated (Box 6, Folder 102)
    - 1854 January 3-1859 December 30 (Box 6, Folder 103-118)
    - 1859-undated (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - 1860 January 1-1862 December 29 (Box 7, Folder 120-126)
    - 1862-undated (Box 7, Folder 127)
    - 1863 January 15-1865 December 23 (Box 7, Folder 128-138)
    - 1865-undated (Box 7, Folder 139)
    - 1866 January 9-December 31 (Box 8, Folder 140-141)
    - 1866-undated (Box 8, Folder 142)
    - 1867 January 17-December 31 (Box 8, Folder 143-145)
    - 1867-undated (Box 8, Folder 146)
    - 1868 January 14-1869 December 30 (Box 8, Folder 147-152)
    - 1869-undated (Box 8, Folder 153)
    - 1870 January 4-December 30 (Box 8, Folder 154-156)
    - 1870-undated (Box 8, Folder 157)
    - 1871 January 9-December 16 (Box 8, Folder 158-159)
    - 1872 January 5-December 27 (Box 9, Folder 160-163)
    - 1872-undated (Box 9, Folder 164)
    - 1873 January 16-1874 December 31 (Box 9, Folder 165-174)
    - 1874-undated (Box 9, Folder 175)
    - 1875 January 6-December 23 (Box 9, Folder 176-182)
    - 1875-undated (Box 9, Folder 183)
    - 1876 January 4-December 30 (Box 10, Folder 184-192)
    - 1876-undated (Box 10, Folder 193)
    - 1877 January 2-1879 May 30 (Box 10, Folder 194-201)
    - 1879 June 5-1897 December 18 (Box 11, Folder 202-216)
    - 1898 April 1-1936 April 6 (Box 12, Folder 217-218)
    - Undated, A-Z (Box 12, Folder 219)
      Alphabetically arranged.
    - Letterbook (L.W. Bacon), 1874-1876 (Box 12, Folder 220)
  - Subject file, 1830-1896; Series II
    This series contains deeds, lists, and other business papers of Leonard Bacon, T. R. Bacon, and B. W. Bacon. It also includes two lists of Leonard Bacon's sermons and discourses; maps of Connecticut and Massachusetts, 1662; a Biblical musical score; index of reading subjects; and biographical data concerning Michael and Leonard Bacon. The folders are arranged alphabetically by subject matter.
    - Bacon, Catherine, acknowledgement of funds from, 1882 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Bacon, (George?), lock of hair, Undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Bacon, Leonard, appraisal of estate; accounting of business affairs; certificate of last will and testament, 1872, 1882 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Bacon, Leonard, biographical data and list of publications, 1802-1881 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Bacon, Michael, Undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Bacon, Rev. Dr., name plate, Undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Biblical musical score and excerpts from the Bible, Undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Boston, Hartford, and Erie Railroad Company, one share of stock owned by Leonard Bacon, 1865 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Deeds and taxable list of Leonard Bacon, 1857-1858, 1860 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Envelopes and calling cards, 1915-undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Hampton Normal School--teacher's reports (Rebecca T. Bacon)(xerox), 1869-1871 (Box 13, Folder 10a)
    - Index of subjects from readings, for future bibliographical reference, B. W. Bacon and L. W. Bacon, 1847-1848 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Lists of L. W. Bacon trust fund accounts; detailed list of household furniture; itemized price list of store goods, 1832, 1894-1896, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Lists of donations to Reverend L. Bacon, 1830, 1833, undated (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Maps, Connecticut and Massachusetts, 1662 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Maps, New Hampshire, Undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Old South Church, centennial celebration program, 1830 September 14 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Petition and acts regarding railroad fares, 1871 (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Photographs, unidentified, Undated (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Proclamation of Thomas Fitch, colonial governor, photocopy of, 1763 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Quit Claim Deed, certificate of transfer, Thomas R. Bacon, 1880, 1882, 1885 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Receipts for Bacon, B. W., from Phillips Academy, 1837-1838 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Sermons and Discourses by Leonard Bacon, list of, 1839 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Tracing, unidentified, photocopy of, Undated (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Wadsworth, Daniel, estate of, 1882 (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - Manuscripts, 1729-1881; Series III
    This series begins with essays, sermons, articles, and other writings of Leonard, Leonard W., and T. R. Bacon, respectively. Following this is a section relating to various church organizations, then a section concerning other clubs, committees, and town meetings. Writings of others ensues, among which the description of the scandal and trial surrounding Leonard Bacon's sister and Alexander McWhorter, written by Catherine Beecher, is notable. After this where is a larger section of unidentified or anonymous works, many of which are probably by members of the Bacon family. The folders are arranged alphabetically by title, subject, or name of the organization, except under writings of others, arranged by author's name. At the end of the series, there are seven folders containing miscellaneous writings, usually very short or fragmentary, covering a wide range of topics, from notes on Akkadian inscriptions to thoughts on ecclesiastical and governmental bodies. Many items concern notes and commentary on Biblical passages. Much of the material in this series is of general historical interest, for example the copied excerpts from the journal of Ezra Stiles, under writings of others.
    - Bacon, Leonard
      - "Days of Our Years, The...", 1862 (Box 13A, Folder 1)
      - "Giving the Charge in an Ordination: What is it?", Undated (Box 13A, Folder 2)
      - Journal, fragment of, 1817-1819 (Box 13A, Folder 3)
      - Journal, copy of a fragment, 1817 (Box 13A, Folder 4)
      - Poetry, Undated (Box 13A, Folder 5)
      - "Reformed Church, Again", Undated (Box 13A, Folder 6)
      - "Unit of Value and Honest Money", Undated (Box 13A, Folder 7)
      - Valedictory at Andover, 1823 (Box 13A, Folder 8)
      - "Valedictory Oration on the Prospects of our Country", 1820 (Box 13A, Folder 9)
      - "Warnerian Theory, The", 1872 (Box 13A, Folder 10)
    - Bacon, Leonard W.
      - American and Foreign Christian Union, address to board of directors, 1869 (Box 13A, Folder 11)
      - "Presuming too Much," letter to editors, 1869 (Box 13A, Folder 12)
      - Resignation from Woodland Church, Undated (Box 13A, Folder 13)
    - Bacon, T. R.
      - "An Agricultural Life in its Effect on the Mind and Character", 1870 (Box 13A, Folder 14)
      - "Characteristics and Success of Women in Literature", 1869 (Box 13A, Folder 15)
      - "Chinese in America", 1869 (Box 13A, Folder 16)
      - "Christianity, the True Philanthropy", 1869 (Box 13A, Folder 17)
      - "Civilization Dependent on Christianity", 1870 (Box 13A, Folder 18)
      - "Comparative Merits of the Courses of Study Pursued at Yale and Harvard", 1870 (Box 13A, Folder 19)
      - "Decision", Undated (Box 13A, Folder 20)
      - "Fessenden, William Pitt", 1870 (Box 13A, Folder 21)
      - "Government of Large Cities in a Republic", Undated (Box 13A, Folder 22)
      - "Knowledge is Power", 1870 (Box 13A, Folder 23)
      - "New England Village", Undated (Box 13A, Folder 24)
      - Poems, Undated (Box 13A, Folder 25)
      - "Pope and Addison", 1870 (Box 13A, Folder 26)
      - Rhymes and limericks, a notebook, 1871 (Box 13A, Folder 27)
      - "Should Government Patronize Literature?", Undated (Box 13A, Folder 28)
      - "Spain", 1868 (Box 14, Folder 29)
      - "United States Ought to Acknowledge the Independence of Cuba", Undated (Box 14, Folder 30)
      - "Use of Translations", 1870 (Box 14, Folder 31)
      - "Will Catholicism Form a Dangerous Element in Our Political System?", Undated (Box 14, Folder 32)
      - "Wooden Spoon", Undated (Box 14, Folder 33)
      - "Would a Further Extension of the Union be Desirable", 1871 (Box 14, Folder 34)
    - Churches
      - Association of Middlesex, report on the state of religion, 1834 (Box 14, Folder 35)
      - Church of the Puritans, matters to be proposed, Undated (Box 14, Folder 36)
      - Congregational Association of New London County, rules, 1789 (Box 14, Folder 37)
      - Congregationalist Church, National Council, minutes of, Undated (Box 14, Folder 38)
      - Congregationalist Churches, invitation to national meeting of, 1865 (Box 14, Folder 39)
      - First Congregational Church, Plymouth, charges brought against by Edward Langdon, Undated (Box 14, Folder 40)
      - Presbyterian Church
        - Act of the General Synod, 1729 (Box 14, Folder 41)
        - "Resolution on the Treatment of Servants," draft for the general assembly, 1836 (Box 14, Folder 42)
        - Presbytery of New York, minutes of a meeting, 1837 (Box 14, Folder 43)
      - South Congregational Church of New Haven
        - Discussion about, Undated (Box 14, Folder 44)
        - Minutes of Council Meeting, 1863 (Box 14, Folder 45)
        - Account of greivances of members, 1863 (Box 14, Folder 46)
    - Committees and clubs
      - American Board in Turkey, translation of article on, 1880 (Box 14, Folder 47)
      - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1862 (Box 14, Folder 48)
      - American Congregational Union, partial report on the bookkeeping, Undated (Box 14, Folder 49)
      - Antislavery Association, meeting and minutes, 1825 (Box 14, Folder 50)
      - Antislavery Association, report to American Colonizational Society, 1825 (Box 14, Folder 51)
      - Association of the Western District of New Haven County, declaration of, 1838 (Box 14, Folder 52)
      - Bible Society, an oration delivered before, 1820 (Box 14, Folder 53)
      - Board of Education, New Haven, minority report, Undated (Box 14, Folder 54)
      - College Society, "What New Duties Does the Existence of State Universities Impose on the Churches?," report, Undated (Box 14, Folder 55)
      - Connecticut Academy of Arts and Sciences, draft of memorial to congress, 1846 (Box 14, Folder 56)
      - Constitutional Congress for the Revision of the State Constitution, 1871 (Box 14, Folder 57)
      - Constitutional Convention, notes on, 1871 (Box 14, Folder 58)
      - General Association of Connecticut, minutes of a meeting, 1836 (Box 14, Folder 59)
      - Litchfield South Association, articles for, Undated (Box 14, Folder 60)
      - New Haven City Missionary Society, report from, 1861-1862 (Box 14, Folder 61)
      - Second National Bank, minutes of meetings, 1834, 1836 (Box 14, Folder 62)
      - Town Meetings
        - New Haven, 1768 February 8-1779 August 16 (Box 14, Folder 63)
        - Unidentified, 1774 November 14, 1784 March 8 (Box 14, Folder 64)
    - Writings of others
      - Bacon, David, notes from sermons of, 1816 (Box 14, Folder 65)
      - Beecher, Catherine E., "The McWhorter Case", 1848 (Box 14, Folder 66)
      - Bisler, Mrs. Charles
        - "Christian World Today...", Undated (Box 14, Folder 67)